<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Xero | Interoperate]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.interoperate.co.uk/blog/categories/xero/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.interoperate.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2012-01-24T06:35:53+07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.interoperate.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jon Wade]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No Fuss Accounting with Xero]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.interoperate.co.uk/blog/2012/01/17/no-fuss-accounting-with-xero/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-17T23:08:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.interoperate.co.uk/blog/2012/01/17/no-fuss-accounting-with-xero</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the things that always catches up with me at this time of year is my year end accounts.  As a freelancer, keeping track of expenses and invoices throughout the year is something that I have always found a pain and it inevitably gets put on the back burner.  I've been using spreadsheets for the last few years and my client invoicing process has always been somewhat manual.  I needed a better system and was prepared to spend some cash if it met my requirements.  I came across <a href="http://www.xero.com">Xero</a> after reading a review in <a href="http://www.pcpro.co.uk/reviews/software/367120/xero">PC Pro</a> and decided to give it a go.  I pay £12+VAT per month which is slightly more that I wanted to pay but having used it for a month or so I would say that you definitely get what you pay for.</p>

<p>Killer features for me are:</p>

<!-- More -->


<ol>
<li>Cloud based / SaaS solution - access from anywhere.  Nothing to install.  No backups to worry about.</li>
<li>Automated bank feed - transactions from my HSBC business current account are sent directly to <a href="http://www.xero.com">Xero</a> to be reconciled.  Reconciliation is simply a matter of categorising the transaction and clicking 'OK'.  It 'learns' from previous transactions so will suggest an appropriate category for most transactions.</li>
<li>Incoming transactions are reconciled against previously generated invoices.</li>
<li>Role based access - my accountant has privileges to be able to do all the normal chart of accounts and year end submissions.</li>
<li>Invoice generation.  I now produce all my invoices through <a href="http://www.xero.com">Xero</a>.  It's really easy to add line items as I go along and then invoice at the end of the month.  Emails are sent directly from <a href="http://www.xero.com">Xero</a> to clients.</li>
<li>VAT returns - I've yet to try this but will be doing this in a couple of weeks.</li>
<li>iPhone App.  A fairly basic app allows you to keep track of accounts and invoices on the go.</li>
</ol>


<p>It couldn't be simpler.  All I now really need to worry about is keeping paper copies of invoices and receipts in a shoe box to keep the tax man happy.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I'm really impressed with <a href="http://www.xero.com">Xero</a>.  It's a fine example of a hosted service that just works and is a pleasure to use.  I can see many small companies that currently use spreadsheets, <a href="http://www.sage.co.uk/">Sage</a> or <a href="http://www.intuit.co.uk/">Quickbooks</a> migrating to <a href="http://www.xero.com">Xero</a> in the coming months.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
